<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons humbly offer'd against the salt-petre bill, which is for importing petre for one year, paying the old duty (5 l. per tun) and selling the King at 75 l. per tun, notwithstanding the Act of Navigation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28735</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885944</idno>
  <idno type="VID">186312</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248536154</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R530</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.13[112]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225216</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885944</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99885944e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 186312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C4:1[109])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons humbly offer'd against the salt-petre bill, which is for importing petre for one year, paying the old duty (5 l. per tun) and selling the King at 75 l. per tun, notwithstanding the Act of Navigation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Saltpeter --  Taxation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Foreign trade regulation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:186312:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:186312:1"/>
            <head>REASONS Humbly Offer'd against The SALT-PETRE Bill, Which is for Importing <hi>Petre</hi> for one Year, Paying the old Duty (5 <hi>l. per</hi> Tun) and Selling the King at 75 <hi>l. per</hi> Tun, notwithstanding the Act of Navigation.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Crown hath no necessity for this Bill, for the Stores at present are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, and if they should be exhausted they may be supplyed from <hi>Holland</hi> without this Bill; and therefore the Officers of the Ordnance (who are not Members of the Honourable House of Commons) do declare that this Bill is a Mystery to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Bill is not for the Interest of the Crown for want of a high Impost, whereby the Crown might import it under <hi>75 l. per</hi> Tun.</p>
            <p>But to Stave off an Impost the poor Tradesmen are made Petitioners, and it is observable that this Petition did not come into the House until the first Case was Printed against this Bill: In which an Impost was proposed, which was generally approved of; insomuch that the Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citors for the Bill, durst not proceed in it till they had got the Tradesmens Petition to offer against an Imposition; because they say, that tho' an Imposition makes it cheap to the Crown, yet it makes it dearer to the Subjects. But this is a Fallacy too, for if the Bill passes without an Impost, it raises <hi>Petre</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> as much as the Impost comes to; and if it Passes with an Impost, it falls the Price as much as the Impost comes to; as for Example, if this Bill Passes without a New Impost, it is expected that <hi>Petre</hi> will be in <hi>Holland,</hi> at Eighty or Ninety Pounds <hi>per</hi> Tun; and if it Passes with a New Impost of Thirty pound <hi>per</hi> Tun, it will be Sold there under Sixty Pound, and then the Crown of <hi>England</hi> will receive Thirty Pound: So that the Bill without an Impost, gives the Thirty Pound <hi>per</hi> Tun to the Dutch, and with an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>post to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> which will make no difference in the Price to any <hi>English</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, except the Sollicitors of this Bill, for such Quantities as they have already bought; and it is not expected from them, that they will afford these Tradesmen this <hi>Petre</hi> as cheap as they can; but that they endeavour by this Bill to disable all others to buy so cheap as they have done.</p>
            <p>And if the Petitioners against this Bill might be heard, it would appear, that the Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens pretences are frivolous and false; and that <hi>Salt-Petre</hi> is a very inconsiderable ingredient in any of their Trades, for the Diers who use most (and therefore are set in the Front of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition) use it only in Bow-dies, and there are not above ten in the Kingdom who die that Colour; and for every twenty Shillings worth of <hi>Salt-Petre</hi> which they use, they use twenty Pounds worth of <hi>Cocheneal,</hi> which is a Commodity prohibited by the same Act of Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and by means thereof, is now at twice the Price in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Holland,</hi> and yet these Diers don't complain for want of <hi>Cocheneal;</hi> nor did they know their want of <hi>Petre,</hi> till the Sollicitors of the Bill told them, and there are twenty other Commodities, which (by Reason of the same Act of Navigation) are now at twice the Price in <hi>England</hi> as they are in <hi>Holland;</hi> and had the Sollicitors of this Bill bought up as great Quantities of any of those other Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities in <hi>Holland,</hi> as they have of <hi>Salt-Petre,</hi> they might have had as many Pretences and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners for importing them, as they have for the Passing of this Bill; which if it doth pass, is to the Discouragement of all other English Subjects and Traders; who depend upon the Laws in being, and lay out their Monies and Trade accordingly; and if such fundamental Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes as the Act of Navigation may be repealed on a sudden, by the instance of two or three Men, no Man can be safe in his dealings; and upon the Confidence of this Act, the <hi>East-India</hi> Company and Interlopers, have given out larger Commissions for <hi>Petre</hi> than ever they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and several Private Gentlemen in <hi>England</hi> have laid out above five thousand Pound apiece in Order to make <hi>Salt-Petre</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and tho' they can't give Security to furnish the Crown, yet by this, and the Expectancy of the return of the <hi>East-India</hi> Ships, the Kingdom hath a greater Expectancy and Security for <hi>Petre,</hi> than ever it had before; and the Sollicitors of the Bill are aware of this, and therefore Press this Bill for one Year, in which they'll accomplish all their private ends, and occasion the carrying out from hence of a above hundred thousand Pounds to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> only to save a few Tradesmen a little Money in the Price of <hi>Salt-Petre,</hi> by which they lose nothing, thô the Price were higher than it is, for they are repaid it in the Sale of their Commodities. And by such means, the <hi>Dutch</hi> (by Computation of the Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi>) have already, since the War, drawn from hence above three Millons of our Money upon the Ballance of Trade, and we are daily running in their Debt, by owing them our Money for their Commodities: And this Bill by discouraging all other Means of supplying the Nation with <hi>Petre,</hi> will put us under a Future Necessity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beholden to the <hi>Dutch</hi> for our Stores, at what Rates they please.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:186312:2"/>
            <p>Against the Salt-Petre Bill.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>